Finding aid for the Barbara Aziz broadcasts collection
Bentley Historical Library
Barbara Aziz broadcasts collection
1988-2014
Bentley Historical Library
Aziz, Barbara Nimri.
2021007 Aa 2
868 digital audio files (online)
0.1 linear feet
Dr. Barbara Nimri Aziz is an Arab American author, anthropologist, and journalist. She founded Radio Tahrir, which broadcasted regularly from circa 1990-2013 over New York City's WBAI Radio. Radio Tahrir was the first radio program in the United States to focus on a wide range of topics pertaining to different Arab and Muslim communities across the world. The materials in this collection are dated from 1988-2014 and include broadcast episodes and episode segments as well as commentaries, documentaries, interviews, news reports, and literary recitations.
This collection is open without restriction.
Donated by Dr. Barbara Nimri Aziz (donor no. 11042 ) in November 2017.
The collection is arranged into 3 series: 1. Radio Tahrir and related material. 2. News broadcasts. 3. Interviews and related material.
Barbara Nimri Aziz was born in Ontario, Canada, in 1940. In 1962, she graduated from Queens University in Kingston, Ontario, with a Bachelor in Arts degree in Biology. Aziz then traveled to India and spent several years assisting Tibetan refugees fleeing Chinese control of Tibet. This work inspired her interest in anthropology. In 1969, she enrolled at the University of London's School of Oriental and African Studies (SOAS). She received a Ph.D. in Anthropology from the SOAS in 1974. Her thesis was entitled "The people of Dingri: a socio-historical portrait of a district in S.W. Tibet."
In circa March 1990, Dr. Aziz established the Radio Tahrir radio magazine, which broadcasted over New York City's WBAI Radio, an affiliate of the Pacifica Radio Network. Radio Tahrir (Radio "Liberation") was the first radio program in the United States dedicated to Arab culture and society. Originally, the program focused on uplifting the voices of members of different Arab communities from around the world. It expanded its coverage in circa 1993 to include the voices of Muslim Americans, during which the program was briefly known as "Arab Voices, Crescent Rising".
Radio Tahrir ultimately sought to highlight Arab and Muslim community members' lived experiences, accomplishments, and challenges, particularly as it related to Islamophobia and civil rights. Radio Tahrir typically aired every week on Tuesdays or Saturdays in 30 or 60 minute episodes. These episodes featured a variety of content, including interviews and discussions with invited guests. In addition to its regular programming, Radio Tahrir also produced documentaries; specials, particularly during the month of Ramadan; and series, such as "Maqam: From Cordoba to Baghdad" (circa 1997), "6 Arab American Poets" (1997), and "Fen Mejnoon with Dean and Maysoon" (2004-2006). The program broadcasted regularly until April 13, 2013.
Radio Tahrir was led by Dr. Aziz, who served as the program's executive director. She also served as host, co-host, or producer. She was supported by dozens of Arab and Muslim volunteers and interns over the years, including Hassen Abdella, Jad Abumrad, Aisha Al-Adawiya, Mona Al-Dahry, Fatima Ashraf, Saadia Aslam, Anisa Bouzianne, Ibrahim Gonzalez, Dave Hall, Nazik Hibatfa, Hussein Ibish, Mahmoud Ibrahim, Mona Iskander, Tamara Issak, Ryme Katkhouda, Dean Obeidallah, Sarah Malaika, Nadja Middleton, Reem Nasr, Sally Sherif, and Maysoon Zayid. Dr. Aziz recruited these volunteers and interns because she viewed Radio Tahrir as a space where Arab and Muslim community members could voice their concerns as well as become more deeply engaged with the public sphere and radio journalism. Many Radio Tahrir volunteer producers were also Muslim women whose positionality offered unique opportunities to address issues like discrimination in mosques and Muslim children's educational needs.
In addition to her work at Radio Tahrir, Dr. Aziz supported WBAI Radio and the Pacifica Network in other ways. She traveled throughout the Middle East, interviewing and providing reports for use in their programs as well as Radio Tahrir. She also spent a significant amount of time in Iraq documenting the impact of the United Nations sanctions in that country in the years following the Invasion of Kuwait. She also hosted the WBAI Radio current affairs program Behind the News from 2000-2002, and participated in other WBAI and non-WBAI programs, including Labbrish, The Morning Show, and TalkBack.
As a result of her work at Radio Tahrir, Dr. Aziz founded the Radius of Arab American Writers Inc. (RAWI) in 1993. RAWI is a national literary and networking organization focused on supporting Arab American writers. She served as RAWI's director until about 2005. Her other professional activities included spending a year (2007-2008) at Algeria's University of Oran as a Fulbright Scholar as well as working and teaching in Syria (from 2009-2012).
Dr. Aziz has published numerous books over the years, including Heir to a Silent Song: Two Rebel Women of Nepal (2001), Swimming up the Tigris: Real Life Encounters with Iraq (2007), Short Features for Radio: A Manual for Broadcast Journalists (2011), and Yogmaya & Durga Devi: Rebel Women of Nepal (2020). She has contributed to several blogs and websites, including CounterPunch, her personal website's blog, and the Radio Tahrir blog.
Dr. Barbara Nimri Aziz currently resides in New York.
The Barbara Aziz broadcasts collection (868 digital audio files (online) and 0.1 linear feet) document Dr. Barbara Nimri Aziz's journalistic career, particularly as it pertained to WBAI Radio's Radio Tahrir, Behind the News, and TalkBack programs. Collection material is dated from 1988-2014 and includes broadcast episodes and episode segments, commentaries, documentaries, interviews, news reports, and recitations.
There is some overlap between the Radio Tahrir and related material series as well as the Interviews and related material series. Researchers are encouraged to consult both series for relevant material.
Arab American authors.; Arab American poetry.; Arab Americans -- Civil rights -- United States.; Arab-Israeli conflict.; Economic sanctions -- Iraq.; Middle East -- Politics and government -- 1945-; Muslims -- Civil rights -- United States.; Women in radio broadcasting.; Women radio producers and directors.; Digital file formats.; Interviews (Sound recordings); Sound recordings.; Aziz, Barbara Nimri.; Radio Tahrir.
- Radio Tahrir and related material, 1989-2014
  The Radio Tahrir and related material series (648 digital audio files (online) and 0.1 linear feet) consists primarily of episodes, episode segments, and unique series associated with the radio magazine, Radio Tahrir.
  Radio Tahrir episodes typically consisted of multiple kinds of content, including commentaries from experts as well as listening audience members, interviews with guests, literary readings and recitations, reports, and/or testimonials. Guests on the program included activists, attorneys, authors, artists, religious and secular community leaders, filmmakers, journalists, musicians, poets, and scholars. Although a wide range of cultural, historical, literary, political, and religious topics relating to different Arabic and/or Muslim communities around the world were discussed on the program, those relating to Iraq, Israel, and Palestine are prominently featured.
  Also included are several special series associated with Radio Tahrir. The most prominent of these series included are "Maqam: From Cordoba to Baghdad" (circa 1997), which focused on Arabic music and featured Simon Shaheen; "6 Arab American Poets" (1997); and "Fen Mejnoon with Dean and Maysoon" (2004-2006), which was co-hosted by Arab American comedians Dean Obeidallah and Maysoon Zayid.
  Other material in this series are several National Alliance of Third World Journalists' Alliance Report episodes as well as physical "6 Arab American Poets" brochures.
  - June 13, 1989, (Alliance Radio Report Special)
    - Part 1 of 2, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:32:48); (Interview with Ghaleb Halasa, studio discussion of modern Arab literature. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: novelist Ghaleb Halasa (Syria); NY poet Layla Jamal; Prof Pierre Kahiyah. Topics: Arab literature, Arab poetry, Middle East, Palestine.)
    - Part 2 of 2, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:30:35); (Damascus-based author Ghaleb Halasa, continuing with studio guests Layla Jamal and Pierre Kahiya. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Novelist Damascus based Ghaleb Halasa (Syria), NY poet Layla Jamal, Prof Pierre Kahiyah. Topics: Arab literature, Arab poetry, Middle East, Palestine.)
  - 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:30:20); (Sout Al-Chab radio program, in Arabic, mother broadcasts to son in prison. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Mona Atway, radio producer, Sout Al-Chab Radio, Beirut. Topics: media, Lebanon, prisoners, Middle East.)
  - 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:23:02); (Kamāl Abū Dīb, who talks about his work and modern literary issues, pan-Arab themes, historical and contemporary, in Damascus. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Kamal Abu Deeb, well known Syrian novelist. Topics: Syria, Arab literature.)
  - 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:30:32); (Interview of American translator and storyteller Inea Bushnaq. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Inea Bushnaq, NY-based Storyteller/translator. Topics: Palestine, Culture, Folktales.)
  - March 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:46); (Images of Arab women in literature and media. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Nadia Hijab, author of "Women Power: Women and Work in the Middle East." Topics: Arab women, Middle East, economy, development.)
  - March 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:32:27); (Mikael on 1920 history and Sharaawi's role in Egypt's women's movement. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Mona Mikael, author and professor of Arabic, NYU, NY. Topics: Arab women, Egypt, Middle East, Huda Sharaawi.)
  - circa March-April 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:25:54); (Boutros recalls his early study of music in Palestine, being a musician. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Peter Boutros, NY-based musician. Topics: Arab music, oud performance, Palestine.)
  - April 11, 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:23:20); (Palestinian resistance leader Intissar Wazir speaks about her work. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Intissar Wazir, Palestinian resistance leader. Topics: Palestine, leadership, independence struggle.)
  - April 18, 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:27:50); (Baqsami speaks about her work, art, exhibitions and gallery. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Thoraya Al-Baqsami, Kuwaiti artist. Topics: Kuwait, art, women, invasion, Iraq.)
  - circa October 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:30:24); (German Arab scholar Birgette Seekemp discusses Arab literature and Palestinian novel, interviewed in Damascus, Syria. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Birgette Seekemp, German scholar of Arabic in Syria. Topics: Arab literature, Syria, Palestine.)
  - November 1, 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:20); (Aziz interviews writer and editor Daoud Talhami (Damascus-based, Palestinian editor, journalist) in Damascus, Syria. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Daoud Talhami, Damascus-based, Palestinian editor, journalist. Topics: Middle East, Palestine, publishing.)
  - November 6, 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:30:25); (Zahaby speaks about life as a writer, influences from US, limits in Syria. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Khairy Al Zahaby, Syrian author, Damascus-based. Topics: Arab literature, Syria.)
  - November 13, 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:29:43); (Discusses 1970s Iraq economic policy, professional class, new UN US sanctions, economy. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Rashid Yakoub, Iraqi economist, engineer, US-based. Topics: Iraq, economic history, economy, sanctions.)
  - December 11, 1990, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:09); (Baqsami speaks about her writing and women's struggle for rights. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Thoraya Al-Baqsami, Kuwaiti artist, recorded in Kuwait. Topics: Kuwait, art, literature, women, recorded in Kuwait.)
  - 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:32:02); (Aziz reflects on those she met in Iraq, during these weeks while bombing is underway, recorded segments of Aziz report in Nasiriya (South Iraq). Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Barbara Nimri Aziz producer, Iraq correspondent, NY-based Mary Kadi reading. Topics: Iraq, Gulf War, anti-war, war, US policies, journalism.)
  - 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:23); (Aziz interviews Mai Masri and Jean Chamoun about filmmaking in Lebanon, in NY. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Mai Masri and Jean Chamoun, Beirut-based filmmakers. Topics: Lebanon, film, Middle East, Arab women.)
  - 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:10:14); (Syed Mohammad Syeed (Sayyid Syeed) comments on anti-Muslim bias and how to counter it. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Sayeed Sayed, PA-based community leader, scholar. Topics: American Muslims, leadership, media.)
  - January 1, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:12); (Aziz commentary regarding Israeli bombings on South Lebanon, program honoring martyr Anwar Yassin, resistance to occupation, vocals by Ferouz. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Producers at Sout Al-Chab Radio, Beirut. Topics: Lebanon, prisoners, occupation resistance.)
    (Partially in Arabic)
  - January 29, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:07); (Barbara Nimri Aziz (BN Aziz) speaks from experiences as correspondent inside Iraq, also music. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: BN Aziz comments on Iraq. Topics: Iraq, UN bombing, sanctions.)
  - February 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:31:34); (Al-Radi reviews international archeological digs and finds in Iraq and current US bombing on Iraq, threat on ancient archeological sites, Iraqi universities. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Selma Al-Radi, Iraqi archeologist, NY-based. Topics: Iraq, sanctions, US current bombing policy, antiquities.)
  - February 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:31:56); (Aziz reflects on images in US press during bombing of Iraq and her first-hand experiences, open phones to listeners. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Barbara Nimri Aziz, producer, Iraq correspondent. Topics: Iraq, Gulf War, anti-war, images of Iraq in US books.)
  - February 12, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:58:31); (Aziz comments on US Muslim civil rights and takes listener calls, interviews filmmakers Mai Masri and Jean Chamoun. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Mai Masri and Jean Chamoun, Beirut-based filmmakers. Topics: US Civil rights, film, Middle East.)
  - February 26, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:48:08); (Kassem speaks about activist career; Hakmoun speaks about work and plays. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Casey Kassem radio producer, Hassan Hakmoun, musician. Topics: Arab America, civil rights activism, West African music.)
  - March 26, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:30:03); (Forzley reports on business exchanges and co-operation of American and Middle East Arabs, and discrimination, civil rights. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Michele Forzley, Boston-based businesswoman. Topics: Arab American community activism, business in Middle East.)
  - May 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:48:06); (Hajjar Ghani and her father describe being bombed by US allies for 42 days. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Hajjar Ghani, Iraqi student; Mohammed Ghani sculptor in Baghdad. Topics: Iraq, children, 1991 bombing (Gulf War).)
  - May 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:23:17); (Al-Radi testifies to her findings after 1991 US bombings on infrastructure, health and ancient treasures and monuments. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Selma Al-Radi, Iraqi archeologist, NY-based. Topics: Iraq, US bombing, sanctions, US policy, antiquities.)
  - May 28, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:32:30); (Ziad Abdul Samad, interviewed in Beirut about civil, humanitarian assistance during conflict interview. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Ziad Abdul Samad, engineer, development officer. Topics: Lebanon civil war, Secours Populaire relief organization.)
  - June 18, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:29:47); (Open phones for listener comments on Ramadan, Iraq, and sanctions. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Baghdad-based writer and critic Jabra Ibrahim Jabra, Iraq sanctions, media. Topics: Ramadan, Islam, Iraq, UN sanctions effects, callins (badly distorted).)
  - June 25, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:33:12); (A visit to Sout Al-Shab radio, Beirut, on war resistance. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Various testimonials. Topics: Lebanon, Media.)
  - July 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 1:02:38); (Jabril speaks about work in Kuwait, result of war in Kuwait, political analysis; Renfrew reviews Salinger book "Secret Dossier". Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Palestinian refugee from Kuwait, Showki Jabril; Nita Renfrew NY-journalist. Topics: Kuwait, Iraq, Palestine, refugees, regional economy.)
  - July 1991, (Special on Medical Issues in Iraq)
    - Part 1 of 2, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:46:21); (Discusses 1970s Iraq economic policy, professional class, new UN sanctions, economy. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Iraqi doctors, Dr Hamid of Iraq Red Cross, Baghdad, Malaysian Dr Shaharom. Topics: Iraq, bombing, health conditions, Arab and Muslim medical assistance.)
    - Part 2 of 2, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:43:17); (Ahmed Jabra reports on needs and assistance, Kerbala doctors report on bombing effects on health and medical conditions, Dr. Al-Murshadi reports on destruction of medical centers by internal and external attacks. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Iraqi doctors, NY-based Dr Amed Jabra, Kerbala Dr Naffi, Dr Kudaiyar Al-Murshadi, Kerbala. Topics: Iraq, sanctions, medical deterioration.)
  - August 20, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 1:23:35); (Water in Middle East special. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Egyptian engineer Mohammed O. Galal; geologist in West Bank Al-Ashri: US based historian Munir Farah. Topics: Egypt, Syria, water resources, Middle East.)
  - October 8, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:29:47); (Aziz interviews Dr. Buthaina Shaabana, author of "Right Hand Left Hand", in Damascus, Syria. Hosts/Producer: Barbara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Buthaina Shaaban, Damascus-based writer, Professor of English, translator. Topics: Arabic literature, Middle East.)
  - October 22, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:24:05); (Reports on women in Palestinian resistance, gains and losses, Arab women and their relation to western women, efforts in media and academia. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Suha Sabagh, Arab Women's Studies Center, director, DC. Topics: women, Palestine, peaceful resistance, Middle East, media.)
  - October 29, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:30:54); (Each guest describes the work of their committee in the USA, to build solidarity and educate Americans. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Arab America Institute director, Helen Samhan, Palestine Solidarity Committee, Riyad Khourey; AAUG director Ghada Talhami. Topics: Arab American community activism in US, elections, Palestine solidarity, Arab American University Graduate Association work in USA.)
  - November 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:51:38); (Alliance Report: Al-Radi testifies to her findings after 1991 US bombings on infrastructure, and doctors report on breakdown of health conditions and facilities. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Selma Al-Radi, archeologist, NY-based, Kerbala Hosp doctors. Topics: Iraq, sanctions, health facilities.)
  - November 5, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:29:07); (Thoraya Al-Baqsami interview)
  - November 26, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:31:14); (Episode on water and the Golan, featuring Undercurrents reports)
  - December 3, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:31:04); (Interview in Arabic about Munir Bashir's work with selections; translated by Mary K. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Munir Bashir, Iraqi composer and virtuoso. Topics: Iraq, Music, Munir Bashir.)
  - December 10, 1991, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:28:28); (Aziz elaborates on restrictions on sanctioned US diplomats, listeners' calls. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Iraq, US restrictions on diplomats. Topics: Iraq, sanctions, US policy, United Nations.)
  - 1992, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:25:36); (Aziz interviews Washington, DC-based author of "Fields of Fig and Olive," Kathryn Abdul Baki. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Kathryn Abdul Baki, Washington-based author. Topics: Arab American literature, Palestine.)
  - 1992, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:11:27); (Akram Zatari interviews Moufida Tlatli, Tunisian director of "Silences of the Palace"; translated by Jacqueline Hazzi (English and French). Hosts/Producer: Akram Zatari. Interviewees/Guests: Moufida Tlatli, Tunisian director of "Silences of the Palace". Topics: film, Tunisia.)
  - February 18, 1992, (Alliance Report and "Radio Tahrir" joint episode)
    - Part 1 of 2, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:43:47); (Musloom talks about radio voice of the Arab community and changes in political atmosphere. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Richard Musloom, WFUV (NY) radio host. Topics: Arab American, activism, media.)
    - Part 2 of 2, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:44:42); (Nibari speaks from Kuwait, on upcoming election; PHR Geiger's and Kirshner's presentations to conference on deaths of Palestinian prisoner. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: Abdallah Nibari, Kuwaiti MP; Drs J Gieger and R Kirshner, Physicians for Human Rights (PHR). Topics: Kuwait, democracy, Palestine, prisoners, Human Rights.)
  - March 1992, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:29:53); (Aziz interviews women (Edith Koniky, Meena Alexander, Barbara E Smith, Claire Coss) celebrating Women's History Month. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: American writers Edith Koniky, Meena Alexander, Barbara E Smith (Feminist Press), Claire Coss. Topics: world literature, Women.)
  - March 10, 1992, 1 digital audio files (Duration: 0:29:41); (Aziz interviews poet DH Melhem about her work, with readings. Hosts/Producer: Barabara Nimri Aziz. Interviewees/Guests: DH Melhem, NY-based poet. Topics: Arab American literature, poetry.)